Guide to the World Performance Project at Yale Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
World Performance Project at Yale records
2006-2012
YCAL MSS 1147
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.34
(9 boxes) + 1 roll
The World Performance Project at Yale Records include performance programs, posters, and other publicity materials; participant contracts and agreements; administrative files; and audiovisual material and digital files that document the Project's performances, workshops, discussions, symposia and other events and activities from 2006 through 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Box 7 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Digital surrogates may be viewed in the reading room. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 8-9 (digital media): Restricted fragile material. Digital surrogates may be viewed in the reading room. Consult Access Services for further information.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Publicity, 2006-2012. II. Contracts and Agreements, 2006-2012. III. Administrative Files, 2006-2012. IV. Audiovisual Material. V. Digital Media, 2006-2012.
World Performance Project at Yale, 2006-2012
In 2006, Joseph Roach, Charles C. and Dorathea S. Dilley Professor of Theater and English at Yale University, received a Distinguished Achievement Award from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation. The award recognizes scholars who have made significant contributions to the humanities and enlarged opportunities for scholarship at their institutions, and intends to provide recipients and their institutions with resources to deepen their scholarship. Through funding provided with the award, Professor Roach established the World Performance Project at Yale (WPP). The three-year project was extended through 2012, with funding from the University and residual funds from the initial grant. Affiliated with the Yale College Theater Studies Program and the Whitney Humanities Center, the Project brought artists from throughout the United States, Europe, Latin America, Africa, and Asia to perform and engage in conversations with members of the Yale and the greater New Haven communities. In 2007, the Yale Repertory Theatre joined the World Performance Project in presenting international work and artists in the first of the "No Boundaries" season series, and continued the series after the WPP ended in 2012.
As described in its first season brochure, "The World Performance Project (WPP) promotes programs in performance studies across departments at Yale. An interdiscipline that draws from the arts, humanities, and human sciences (theater, drama, dance, visual arts, speech, linguistics, anthropology, sociology), performances studies defines as its objects cultural performances of all kinds, from theatrical presentations to rites of passage, and it expands it frontiers anywhere significant performances are likely to take place, from Yorubaland to Disneyland. … With performance-as-research in mind, the WPP presents performances, workshops, master classes, lectures, and residencies by artists and scholars working in dance, theater, music, performance art, and cultural performance. The WPP strives to frame each event in pre- and post-performance discussion in an effort to deepen the critical reception of the work. Serving as a central presenting organization, the WPP initiates performance-related events, as it assists and collaborates with departments and programs through the university seeking to enhance their curriculum through live performance."
Professor Roach served as principal investigator of the Project; Emily Coates, a lecturer in the Yale College Theater Studies program and a professional dancer, served as artistic director; and Kathryn Krier, who was design advisor for the Theater Studies Program, served as technical director/production manager.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Joseph R. Roach, 2013.
Scope and Contents
The World Performance Project at Yale Records include performance programs, posters, and other publicity materials; participant contracts and agreements; administrative files; and audiovisual material and digital files that document the Project's performances, workshops, discussions, symposia and other events and activities from 2006 through 2012.
- Publicity, 2006-2012; Series I; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically by date of performance/event.
  Scope and Contents
  Performance and event programs, posters, flyers and tickets.
  - 2006-2007 Season
    - Season brochure (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Don't Start Me to Talking or I'll Tell You Everything I Know: Sayings from the Life and Writings of Junebug Jabbo Jones (Volume I), written and performed by John O'Neal, 2006 October 20-22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Poster (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Death & Resurrection by Naguib Mahfouz, 2006 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Part of the Masrah Arab Egyptian Theatre Festival
    - Women Dreamt Horses by Daniel Veronese, 2006 November (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Field trip to Performance Space 122, BAiT: Buenos Aires In Translation, New York
    - Singing the Way Home: A Work Demonstration by Ang Gey Pin, 2006 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Choreographers and Choreographies," a talk by Susan Leigh Foster, 2007 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Framed poster (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - The Other Here by Big Dance Theater, lecture demonstration and workshops with Dr. Sachiyo Ito and Annie-B Parson and members of the company, 2007 January 18-19 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Includes performance program from the performance of The Other Here at the Japan Society, New York (2007 February 7-10)
      - Framed poster (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Wesleyan 365, Wesleyan University, 2007 February 5-11 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Program for Wesleyan University's event celebrating 365 Days/365 Plays by Suzan-Lori Parks which included "Joseph Roach & Yale 365"
    - Pouring Tea: Narratives of Black Gay Men of the South written and staged reading by E. Patrick Johnson, 2007 February 26 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Framed poster (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Headlong Dance Theater workshop, 2007 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - A Room of One's Own: Women and Power in the New America, written, directed, and performed by Coco Fusco, 2007 March 30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Framed poster (Box 4, Folder 71-72)
    - Yale Dance Theater performance at the Baryshinikov Arts Center, New York, 2007 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Joan Acocella talk, 2007 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 2007-2008 Season
    - Season brochure (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Includes brochure for Yale Repertory Theatre season, including a series of international performances co-sponsored with WPP
    - Gone Missing created by The Civilians company, directed and written by Steve Cosson, 2007 September 26 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - The Veiled Monologues, written and directed by Adelheid Roosen, 2007 October 23-27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Biographical / Historical
      Presented by WPP and Yale Repertory Theatre
      Includes program for the Symposium on Cultural Dislocation, Universal Human Rights & Theater, presented in conjunction with the theater production (October 25, 2007)
      - Poster (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Milk of Amnesia/Leche de Amnesia written and performed by Carmelita Tropicana (Alina Troyano), 2007 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - The Joban Fugue, work-in-process by David Michalek (excerpts and discussion with Michalek), 2007 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Angelo Moore as Dr. Madd Vibe, 2007 December 6 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Perú Negro ensemble, 2008 January 30-31 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Sclavi/The Son of an Emmigrant by Farm in the Cave Theatre Studio, 2008 April 3-5 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Includes program for Symposium on Interdisciplinary Performance and Cricitcism, presented in conjunction with Sclavi (April 4, 2008)
    - Don't Look Back! A Rock 'n Roll Orpheus presented by THST 309: Project O, 2008 April 18-19 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Includes script
    - Looking Back/Looking Forward conference, 2008 April 15-19 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      A week-long conference of lectures, music, dance-theater and film presentations featuring versions of the myth of Orpheus
  - 2008-2009 Season
    - No Boundaries: A Series of Global Performances season brochure, 2008 September (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Presented by YPP and Yale Repertory Theatre
    - England, written and performed by Tim Crouch, 2008 October 28, 30 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Presented by WPP and Yale Center for British Art
    - Festival of International Dance at Yale, 2008 November 9-15 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Part of the No Boundaries series; included performances of works choreographed by Yasmeen Godder, Julyen Hamilton, Opiyo Okach, Yvonne Rainer, and talk backs, workshops, a panel discussion with the choreographers moderated by Thomas F. DeFrantz, and a lecture by Peggy Phelan
      - Poster (Box 3, Folder 59)
      - Banner (Box 10 (Roll))
    - MOSAIC, An Interactive Work-in-Progress about Race and Masculinity written and performed by Gamal J. Palmer, 2008 December 4-5 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - One of the Damned Few co-written by Bud Thorpe and Toni Dorfman; performed by Bud Thorpe, 2009 January 16-18 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - the break/s: a mixtape for stage written and performed by Marc Bamuthi Joseph, 2009 January 22-24 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Part of the No Boundaries series
      Includes program for "Performing the Breaks, African American Aesthetic Structures," a lecture by Thomas F. Defrantz (January 21, 2009)
      - Poster (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Witness to the Ruins by Mapa Teatro Laboratorio De Artistas; conceived and devised by Heidi and Rolf Abderhalden, 2009 March 26-28 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Includes program for the related symposium, Mapping Memory: Performance, Witnessing and Place (March 27, 2009)
      - Poster (Box 10 (Roll))
    - Just Dance: a weekend of dance workshops with Bill T. Jones & Arnie Zane Dance Company and Urban Bush Women, 2009 April 18-19 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Yale MFA Video/Performance, 2009 April 23 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Presented by the Yale University Art Gallery; Post Traumatic Trance Disorder, Video + Performance by Tamar Ettunn and Departure/Arrival Video + Performance by Billie Lee "made possible by the Yale World Performance Project."
    - New Works in Dance and Music Composition, 2009 May 1 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      Showing of works created collaboratively by students in THST 387 Advanced Dance Composition and MUSIC 312/412 Composition Seminar
    - Hearing B(l)ind: a MIND (Motion in Dialogue) Production, a dance theater composition choreographed by Emily Coates and Bronwen MacArthur, 2009 May 4 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - 2009-2010 Season
    - No Boundaries series season advertisements, 2009 September (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Emergent Global Corporealities: Dance Technologies and Circulations of the Social, a conference hosted by Thomas F. DeFrantz and Harmony Bench, 2009 October 18 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Sponsored by Center for Transnational Cultural Analysis, Slippage: Performance|Culture|Technology, and WPP
      - Movement Research Performance Journal #36, 2010 January (Box 3, Folder 61)
        Includes article on the conference, The World Performance Project at Yale," by Rachel Bernsen
    - Wormwood written and designed by Theatre of the Eighth Day (Teatr Ómego Dnia) ensemble, 2009 November 5-7 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      Includes program for "The Poetics of 'Going Against the Tide': 45 Years of the Theatre of the Eight Day," a lecture by Kathleen Cioffi, with a response by Krystyna Illakowicz (November 2, 2009)
    - Ivy Dance Exchange: Brown - Harvard - Yale, Harvard Dance Center, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 2009 December 4-5 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - The Be(A)st of Taylor Mac, written and performed by Taylor Mac, 2010 January 28-30 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      Part of the No Boundaries series; included performances of works choreographed by Yasmeen Godder, Julyen Hamilton, Opiyo Okach, Yvonne Rainer, and talk backs, workshops, and a panel discussion with the choreographers moderated by Thomas F. DeFrantz, and a lecture by Peggy Phelan
      Includes program for "The Gentrification of Freakishness," a lecture by Tavia Nyong'o with a response by Joanne Meyerowitz (January 25, 2010)
    - Global Movers: A Contemporary Dance Workshop Series, 2010 February 26-April 16 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      Included workshops by Jill Johnson, Yoko Higashino, I-Ling Liu, and Andreya Ouamba
    - MESs created by Baby-Q, performed by Yoko Higashino, 2010 March 25-27 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      Includes program for "Baby Q and the Bio-Politics of Japanese Choreography in the Wake of Butoh," a lecture by Reginald Jackson with a response by Paige McGinley (March 24, 2010)
    - Purple Feedback: Dance, Music and Technology at Yale, 2010 April 28 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      Works created and performed by students in MUSIC 395 Composition and Performance of Music, Multi-Media Art and Technology, and THST 387 Advanced Dance Composition
  - 2010-1011 Season
    - The English Institute: Author, Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 2010 September 10-12 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      Included presentation, "Authorship and the Literature of Movement," by the World Performance Project at Yale (Marie Borroff, Emily Coates, Lacina Coulibaly, Kathryn Krier, and Joseph Roach)
    - The Case of the Spectator, created and performed by María Jerez, 2010 September 23-25 (Box 2, Folder 44)
      Includes program for "My Screens are Killing Me, or Watching Hurts," a lecture by Sue-Ellen Case with a response by Laura Wexler (September 22, 2010)
    - AFST 435a/THST335a West African Dance: Traditional to Contemporary taught by Lacina Coulibaly, 2010 Fall (Box 2, Folder 45)
      Poster for Yale course
    - Dance Workshop Series with Jill Johnson, 2010 November 3-17 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Make Contact: Dance Studies at Yale, 2011 Spring (Box 2, Folder 47)
      Poster for History of Dance, Advanced Dance, and Transcultural Collaboration in Performance courses
    - Yale Dance Theater Pilot Program, 2011 January (Box 2, Folder 48)
      Poster for the pilot of a faculty-sponsored extracurricular dance initiative, the reconstruction of Eight Jelly Rolls choreographed by Twyla Tharp in 1971
    - The Method Gun written by Kirk Lynn and created by Rude Mechs, 2011 February 23-26 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      Part of the No Boundaries Series
      Includes program for "The Stellar Burdens of Shame," a lecture by Robin Bernstein with responses by Charlotte Brathwaite, Sunder Ganglani, and Christopher Grobe
      - Poster (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Nameless forest, choreographed and directed by Dean Moss in collaboration with Sungmyung Chun, 2011 March 31-April 2 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      Includes program for "Replacing One Imagination Culture With Another: A Symbolic Exchange," a lecture by Ralph Lemon, and "Touching Worlds: Performing the Cross-Cultural in/through Nameless forest ," a lecture by Elizabeth Son (March 30, 2011)
      - Poster (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - 2011-2012 Season
    - Mesopotamia by Robert Myers, 2011 October 21-22 (Box 2, Folder 51)
      A staged reading with Kathleen Chalfant
    - Engagement Féminin: An Evening of West African Contemporary Dance choreographed by Auguste Ouédraogo and Bienvenue Bazié, 2011 November 3-5 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - Poster (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Think Jam: Improvisation Across Disciplines symposium, 2011 November 5 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      Part of the No Boundaries Series; "An improvised jam session with dancers, musicians, poets, and scholars, in which disciplines collide and co-mingle, in dialogue with Engagement Féminin"
    - Master of Tradition, Pandit Chitresh Das, 2011 November 5 (Box 2, Folder 54)
      Traditional Kathak dance
      - Poster (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Spectral Scriabin with Eteri Andjaparidze, Piano and Jennifer Tipton, Lighting, 2012 February 10-11 (Box 2, Folder 55)
      Includes program for "A Colloquium with Eteri Andjaparidze"
      - Poster (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - The Rehearsal by Cuqui Jerez, 2012 March 23-24 (Box 2, Folder 56)
      Includes program for "Rehearsing Intimacy: Cuqui Jerez's Do-overs," a lecture by Ramón H. Rivera-Servera with response by Dominika Laster (March 22, 2012)
      - Poster (Box 3, Folder 67)
- Contracts and Agreements, 2006-2012; Series II; 3.09; (3 boxes)
  Arranged chronologically.
  Contracts and agreements between the World Performance Project at Yale and performers, speakers, and other participants in Project performances and events.
  - 2006-2007 Season
    - John O'Neill, 2006 October-November (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - 365 Days/365Plays, 2007 October-November (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - Ang Gey Pin, 2006 November-December (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Big Dance Theater, 2006 December–2007 January (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Pouring Tea, 2007 February (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - Coco Fusco, 2007 February (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - Other, 2006 September–2007 January (Box 5, Folder 79)
      Includes Allegra Kent, Dina Amin, Robert Swinston, Marvin Carlson, Patrick Crowley, Susan L. Foster
  - 2007-2008 Season
    - The Civilians, 2007 September (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - The Veiled Monologues, 2007 July-October (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Carmelita Tropicana, 2007 October (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - The Joban Fugue, 2007 November (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Dr. Madd Vibe, 2007 December (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Perú Negro, 2006 September–2008 January (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Farm in the Cave Theater Studio, 2008 April (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - 2008-2009 Season
    - England, 2008 July-October (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - Festival of International Dance, 2008 September–2009 April (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - MOSAIC, 2008 December (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - the break/s, 2009 January (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - One of the Damned Few, 2009 January (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - Witness to the Ruins, 2009 March (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - Hearing B(l)ind, 2009 May (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - Other, 2009 February-June (Box 5, Folder 94)
      Includes Training at Double Edge Theatre permission forms, Bill T. Jones and Arnie Zane Dance Company, and David Barreda
  - 2009-2010 Season
    - Emergent Global Corporealities conference, 2009 October-December (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Wormwood, 2009 June-October (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - Taylor Mac, 2010 January 31 (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Baby-Q, 2010 February 15 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - 2010-2011 Season
    - The Case of the Spectator, 2010 September 24 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - The Method Gun, 2010 November–2011 February (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Nameless forest, 2011 April 2 (Box 5, Folder 101)
- Administrative Files, 2006-2012; Series III; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arranged by type of material.
  Files include a proposal for extension of the funding of the Project and supporting documents; a memorandum regarding the Project's website; lists of Project participants, publications, and press; and publications containing articles documenting the Project.
  - ITS Web Services, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - World Performance Project at Yale proposal for extension funding, 2008 September 29 (Box 6, Folder 107-108)
    Includes letter from Joseph Roach to Yale University President Richard Levin bound with a "proposal that outlines the program's mission and design, and reviews past and future initiatives"; accompanied by bound volume containing WPP course descriptions, funded project summaries, guests artists, speakers and lecturers, selected press coverage, and selected publicity materials
  - Lists
    - "Affiliated Scholars and Artists, 2006-2012" (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - "Bibliography of Publications, 2006-2012" (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - "Press, 2006-2012" (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - "Print Archive Listing, 2006-2012" (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - "Media Archive", 2012 April 12 (Box 6, Folder 113)
  - Theater; Volume 40, Number 1, 2010 (Box 6, Folder 114)
    Postglobal Dance; Special Issue Editors Emily Coates and Joseph Roach
  - Harlequin Magazine: journal of the performing arts…, 2006 December–2007 March (Box 6, Folder 115)
    Published by Yale College students; supported in part by the WPP
    Issues 2 and 3
- Audiovisual Material, 2006-2012; Series IV; 0.21; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Digital surrogates may be viewed in the reading room. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Recordings of performances and a lecture demonstration on digital videocassettes, and recordings of Yvonne Rainer on audiocassette.
  - Recordings of performances, lecture demonstration on four digital videocassettes (Box 7, Folder 116-118)
  - Recordings of "Yvonne Rainer in the 21st Century" on one audiocassette (Box 7, Folder 119)
- Digital Media, 2006-2012; Series V; 2.0; (2 boxes)
  Restricted fragile. Digital surrogates may be viewed in the reading room. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Recordings of performances, talks, and interviews, as well as photographs and files and screen shots of WPP website on CDs, DVDs, and USB drives.
  - Recordings of performances, talks, and interviews on 97 DVDs (Box 8)
  - Recordings of performances, talks, and interviews on 13 CDs and 42 DVDs (Box 9)
  - Screen shots of WPP website on one CD (Box 9)
  - Photographs and files on two thumb drives (Box 9)